Thanks very much for coming, and welcome to this talk.
非常感谢大家的到来 欢迎参加这次演讲
Delighted to be talking to Slavoj Zizek.
很高兴与斯拉沃热·齐泽克交谈
He is the iconoclastic philosopher of our time, known for giving voice to the profound, the absurd, and everything in between.
他是我们时代的标志性哲学家 以表达深刻、荒谬及其间一切而闻名
Among his many books are The Sublime Object of Ideology,
他的众多著作中包括《意识形态的崇高对象》
Living in the End Times, and more recently, Pandemic, as well as Hegel in a Wired Brain, and Surplus Enjoyment, a guide for the non perplexed, really critical difference.
《末日生活》以及近期的《大流行》 还有《连线大脑中的黑格尔》和《剩余享乐：给不惑者的指南》 这是一本关于不困惑、真正关键差异的指南
And he tells me he's now got three more books emerging in the autumn, including Freedom, A Disease Without Cure and Too Late to Awaken, is that the other term?
他告诉我 他现在还有三本书即将在秋季出版 包括《自由 一个无药可治的疾病》和《太晚以至于无法觉醒》 那是另一个术语吗
So what we'll do is we'll have 30 minutes where we will talk and then we'll turn for a Q&A with about 15 minutes for that.
所以我们将进行30分钟的对话 然后我们将进行大约15分钟的问答环节
So in terms of the life and work, yeah, there's this question about life.
所以就生活和工作而言 是的 有一个关于生活的问题
Slavoj, should we start with often very, very driven people have a deep lying, underlying trauma as we were discussing.
斯拉沃热 我们是否应该从经常非常非常有动力的人开始 正如我们所讨论的那样 他们有着深深的、潜在的创伤
So what is your trauma?
那么 你的创伤是什么
In some sense, I'm not kidding.
在某种意义上 我并不是在开玩笑
Life itself.
生活本身
I don't think I existed before theory.
我不认为我在理论出现之前就已经存在了
And I'm so corrupted that even when I watch a movie or read a novel, my mind is always, how can I use it in my theory afterwards?
我如此堕落 以至于即便我在看电影或读小说时 我的脑海总是想着 我之后如何在我的理论中使用它
And I notice details.
而且我注意到细节
For example, did you see that it's not so good, but it's based on video game, the first season of the series, The Last of Us, post acapelipity.
比如 你有没有注意到 它并不是那么好 但它基于视频游戏 该系列的第一季“最后生还者” 后末日世界
For me, of course, as a leftist.
对我来说 当然 作为一个左派
I think it's episode five, where the two, father figure and the girl walker, and enter a city which is well organized in these survivalist terms.
我认为是第五集 那两个人 父亲形象和女孩走着 进入一个根据生存策略而组织良好的城市
They share everything.
他们分享一切
And then, I don't know who, I think Pedro Pascal, the guy, but you have communism here.
然后 我不知道是谁 我想是佩德罗·帕斯卡 那个人 在其中有共产主义
And they simply say, yes, so what, we have communism, yes.
他们简单地说 是的 那又怎样 我们有共产主义 是的
And I think this is what we will need.
我认为这就是我们所需要的
If things go on like this, look at you here in England, you are now almost as bad and without in Slovenia, public health service and so on, everything collapsing.
如果事情继续这样发展 看看你们在英国 你们现在几乎和斯洛文尼亚一样糟糕 没有公共卫生服务等 一切都在崩溃
And just imagine a new crisis of whatever sort.
只要想象一下任何类型的新危机
It's clearly that the market will not do it, that we will need, I'm a communist pessimist, we will need more some kind of a war communism, emergency state, but I'm losing time.
显然 市场不会解决问题 我是一个共产主义悲观主义者 我们将需要某种战时共产主义 紧急状态 但我正在浪费时间
No, no, you're not, that's really important.
不 不 你没有 这真的很重要
So I want to ask you about the end, because you've been writing for a long time, you were talking about melancholia and how you quite like it because it is the end.
所以我想问你关于末日的问题 因为你已经写了很长时间 你谈到了抑郁症 你很喜欢它 因为它就是末日
And there are virtues to ends where something emerges, but then if it's just a total collapse, then that's a bad idea.
如果在末日中有某些东西出现 那么末日是有好处的 但如果它只是彻底崩溃 那就是个坏主意
And in surplus enjoyment, you've turned to that living in the end times, which is quite some time ago you were talking about it.
在《剩余享乐》中 你已转向于末日时期 这是很久以前你谈论的
So to ask you a question you ask in Hegel in A Wired Brain,
所以让我问你一个你在《连线大脑中的黑格尔》中提出的问题
Are we living in a dystopian time or a time of dystopian fantasies, or both?
我们是生活在一个反乌托邦的时代 还是一个反乌托邦幻想的时代 或者两者都是
It's a very good question because this difference is crucial.
这是一个非常好的问题 因为这种区别是至关重要的
The only way I can account for it, let me be precise, which difference?
我唯一能解释的方式 让我准确地说 是哪种区别
Precisely, are we really more or less approaching some kind of end?
确切地说 我们是不是真的或多或少地接近某种终结
Or is it just that in a strange way we are obsessed by the end?
或者 我们以一种奇怪的方式被终结所迷恋
I think both are true, but not in the sense of harmony.
我认为两者都是真的 但不是和谐的意义上
The explanation I have is that we, at the same time,
我的解释是 我们同时生活在我所称的 跟随我的保守的德国朋友彼得·斯洛特代克
we live in an era of cynical reason, where, you know, in the old times, the survival worked like this.
一个玩世不恭的理性时代 你知道 在过去 生存的方式是这样的
You knew something is true, but you pretend that it's not true.
你知道某事是真的 但你假装它不是真的
And you, or you try to explain it away and so on.
或者你试图解释它
Now we are entering a new era, I have in my next book, but also can impress later, of science,
现在我们进入一个新的时代 我在我的下一本书中有写 后面再介绍它 关于科学
where we learned, we, those in power, not me,
我们学会了 那些掌权者 不是我
we learned how to tell objectively at the level of facts the truth,
我们学会了如何在事实的层面上客观地讲述真相
But this very fact immobilizes us.
但这个事实本身使我们停滞不前
Precisely, the fact of talking about it instead of mobilizing us makes us apathetic, inefficient, and so on.
确切地说 谈论它的事实 而不是激励我们 反而使我们变得冷漠、低效 等等
For example, even at the level of art, because I'm here, not at the other place.
例如 即使在艺术的层面上 因为我在这里 不在其他地方
Is there another place in Davis?
在戴维斯还有其他地方吗
I don't know.
我不知道
I can't remember.
我记不清了
Yeah, also.
是的 也是
I forgot.
我忘了
Because if there is a thing I hate, and one of the things where I am tempted to act as a terrorist, like a bomb there.
因为如果有一件事我讨厌 其中一件事让我有冲动像一个恐怖分子一样 放一个炸弹在那里
It's this big art biennales, Venice Castle and so on.
那就是这些大型艺术双年展 比如威尼斯城堡等
Did you notice something about them?
你有没有注意到它们的一些事情
How, in their programmatic notes to begin with, they say we are all under capitalism,
他们如何在他们的纲领性说明中一开始就说 我们都处于资本主义之下
we are part of exploitation, Eurocentric, racist, blah, blah, blah.
我们是剥削、欧洲中心主义、种族主义等等的一部分 等等
And then they go on, and the way Castle and Venice functions are perfect examples of pure capitalist commercialization of art.
然后他们继续下去 但卡斯特尔和威尼斯的运作方式是纯粹资本主义商业化艺术的完美例子
You see the paradox, you are telling it what it is and instead of preventing you, it goes on.
你看到了这个悖论 你告诉它它是什么 它并没有阻止你 而是继续下去
Wasn't the same with, no, it was a little bit north two years ago when you remember the Glasgow Conference on Prince, now no longer just Prince.
不是和 不 两年前在格拉斯哥关于王子的会议时是一样的 现在不仅仅是王子了
Charles was there and in some stupid sense, Although it's not, he basically told the truth, bread danger, blah, blah, blah, but nothing came out of it.
查尔斯在那里 在某种愚蠢的意义上 虽然不是 他基本上讲了真相 供应危机 等等 但什么也没有发生
And this is very close to me, now I enter.
现在已经很接近了 我要开始讲述它
This is as much as you will get from me about life.
这就是你能从我这里得到的关于生活的全部
I know that stance because I have it.
我知道那种立场 因为我有
It's the obsession neurotic stance.
这是一种强迫症的立场
You talk all the time, not to achieve something,
你一直在说话 并不是为了达成某事
but to make it sure that nothing will happen.
而是为了确保什么都不会发生
That's why another detail from life, when I was 50 years ago, 40, in psychoanalysis, you can imagine how it looked.
这就是为什么另一个生活中的细节 当我50年前 40年前 在接受精神分析时 你可以想象它是什么样子
It was a Lacanian psychoanalysis, which means I could be sure that the session will not last more than five, seven minutes.
那是拉康派的精神分析 这意味着我可以确信会议不会持续超过五到七分钟
So I talked all the time.
所以我一直在说话
Why?
为什么
Because I was afraid that if I stop talking for a second,
因为我害怕如果我停止说话哪怕一秒钟
the analyst will ask me some really embarrassing questions.
分析师会问我一些真正尴尬的问题
So you see, this idea of being active to make it sure that nothing will really change, happen.
所以你看 这种为了确保没有真正的变化发生而保持活跃的想法
Can I posit a kind of devil's advocate on that, though, that is it possible, but by talking about the apocalypse, it becomes something that occurs?
我可以提出一个魔鬼的倡导者的观点 尽管如此 通过谈论世界末日 它会变成发生的事情吗
I mean, do you bring it into being,
我的意思是 你会不会让它成为现实
by everybody saying we're in an apocalypse, it's happening, it's going, and then so whenever there's apocalyptic possibility that's immediately grasped and we kind of incite ourselves into an apocalypse.
通过每个人都说我们处于末日 它正在发生 它正在进行 然后每当有末日的可能性 我们就立即抓住它 并且我们自己煽动进入末日
I know I know I know the question but I'm not sure if it functions like that I think it's more this idea if we talk enough about it life will somehow magically just life will just go on
我知道这个问题 但我不确定它是否就是这样工作的 我认为更多的是这个想法 如果我们足够多地谈论它 生命会以某种神奇的方式继续下去
that's why some of you will widely disagree with me because even some Some leftists ask me, are you crazy?
这就是为什么你们中的一些人会强烈不同意我 因为甚至一些左派问我 你疯了吗
How can you support Ukraine?
你怎么能支持乌克兰
You support NATO, you support Western imperialism and so on.
你支持北约 你支持西方帝国主义等等
Well, this is a very strange thing.
嗯 这是一件非常奇怪的事情
I go into it with my Too Late to Awaken book.
我在我的《太晚以至于无法觉醒》一书中深入讨论了这个问题
I tell them, first, I passively speak Russian and my brains are not washed by Western propaganda about Ukraine.
我告诉他们 首先 我被动地说俄语 我的大脑没有被西方关于乌克兰的宣传洗脑
Sorry.
对不起
listening to Russian media all the time, and it's absolutely horrible what I read there.
一直在听俄罗斯媒体 我在那里读到的内容绝对可怕
So which is why I'm jumping, but here we are to jump here and there.
所以这就是为什么我要跳到这个话题 但我们在这里就是要跳来跳去
Another thing that I hate absolutely is this pseudo-deep proverb, you know, apparently multiculturalist.
另一件我绝对讨厌的事情是这种伪深刻的谚语 你知道 显然是多元文化主义的
The enemy is somebody whose side, whose truth, whose story you were not able to listen to.
敌人是你没有能力倾听其立场、其真相、其故事的人
Are you crazy?
你疯了吗
Okay, this applies maybe to small neighborly conflicts, but when you say Hitler is our enemy because we are not ready to listen to his story.
好吧 这可能适用于小的邻里冲突 但当你说希特勒是我们的敌人 因为我们不准备听他的故事
I mean, I did, I read Mein Kampf, a very boring book.
我的意思是 我做了 我读了《我的奋斗》 一本非常无聊的书
And you are even more horrified there.
而你在那里更加恐惧
On the other hand, I think that, of course, we always have a story.
另一方面 我认为 当然 我们总是有一个故事
But in politics, it's not that you enact a story.
但在政治中 并不是你要编一个故事
It's that you do something horrible, and the big problem is to invent a story which covers it up, which allows you to live with the horror.
而是你做了一些可怕的事情 而最大的问题是要发明一个掩盖它的故事 让你能够与恐怖共存
And I think, unfortunately, and my Japanese friends even agree with me here, that that's the case with so-called Western Buddhism, but the same there.
我认为 不幸的是 我的日本朋友们甚至在这里同意我 所谓的西方佛教也是如此
No wonder that, so I read, the most popular spiritual religious, if you call it, but it's not, orientation of big corporate guys today is some kind of a vague pseudo-oriental spiritualism.
难怪我读到 今天大公司高管最流行的精神宗教 如果你称之为宗教 但它不是 取向是某种模糊的伪东方精神主义
Because it's wonderful.
因为它很美妙
You do all the dirty things, people losing jobs, killing.
你做了所有肮脏的事情 人们失业 杀戮
And then you tell yourself, but what is this?
然后你告诉自己 但这怎么了
But isn't life just a fleeting appearance?
生命不就是一种短暂的表象吗
The truth is in me, and so on, and so on.
真理内在于我
I mean, if you have, I respect Buddhism, especially Zen Buddhism.
我的意思是 我尊重佛教 特别是禅宗佛教
But this was, for me, the sobering, one of my, how should I call it, grounding, again, fucking Clive, we are coming back, life experiences.
但这对我来说是发人深省的 我的 我该怎么称呼它 再次接地 回过头来 人生经历
When I read a book, I quoted, Brian Victoria, he is a Japanese, although this type of name, Zen and War, Zen War, something like that.
当我读到一本我引用过的书 Brian Victoria 他是日本人 尽管有这样的名字 禅与战争 禅战争 类似这样的
It describes how almost all of them, there were a couple of million Zen establishment, apart from four or five dissidents, totally supported the Japanese Imperial War.
它描述了几乎所有的人 有几百万的禅宗机构 除了四五个持不同政见者 完全支持日本帝国主义战争
You know, if you are old enough, the big guy popularizer of Zen dies at the tower of Suzuki, Suzuki from hippie times.
你知道 如果你年纪足够大 那个大人物 禅宗的普及者铃木大拙 从嬉皮士时代起就很有名
Yeah, but look at his earlier writings, you know.
是的 但看看他早期的著作 你知道
In late 30s, he wrote a long justification of the Japanese attack on China.
在30年代末 他写了一篇长文为日本对中国的攻击辩护
Not only this, he collaborated with the army because he proposed them a theory with a terrifying example, but which is the truth.
不仅如此 他还与军队合作 因为他提出了一个理论 带有一个可怕的例子 但这是真相
I appreciate him.
我欣赏他
He said, sorry, let's say you are my enemy.
他说 对不起 比方说你是我的敌人
We meet in the battlefield.
我们在战场上相遇
The fight is primitive, I have a knife.
战斗是原始的 我有一把刀
Nonetheless, I'm not totally evil.
尽管如此 我并不完全邪恶
I would find it a little bit problematic to stick my knife into you.
我会觉得把刀子插进你体内有点问题
And he confronts this problem, Suzuki.
铃木面对这个问题
And he says Zen Buddhism has a solution here.
他说禅宗佛教在这里有解决办法
You must go through that, you can call it nirvana, whatever, the zero experience, enlightenment, where you see there is no substantial reality.
你必须经历那个 你可以称之为涅槃 无论什么 零体验 启迪 你看到没有实质性的现实
You are not really active.
你并不是真的在行动
You are just an empty brain observing the crazy dance of phenomena.
你只是一个空白的大脑 观察着现象的疯狂舞蹈
So Suzuki, I'm quoting him, he says, so it's not I as a person will stick my knife into you.
所以铃木 我引用他的话 他说 所以不是我作为一个人会把刀子插进你体内
That's painful, I'm still human at some level.
那很痛苦 我在某种程度上仍然是人
But you should have said, I'm observing a phenomenon,
但你应该说 我在观察一个现象
phenomenal multiplicity where my knife is dancing in the air and somehow it gets stuck into your breast.
多现象的复杂性 我的刀在空中跳舞 不知怎的它卡在了你的胸前
and I can kindly leave it.
我可以仁慈地留下它
So, you know, no.
所以 你知道的 不
But let's talk about paradox as well, because that's really fundamental to your writing and to Zen, in fact, that idea of paradox.
但我们也来谈谈悖论 因为这对于你的写作和禅宗来说确实是基础 事实上 悖论的想法
And in terms also of, I mean, you've talked, and you're sort of talking about it at the moment, you've said that recently things have changed with ideology, that you were saying until now, ideology was just a lie,
还有在某种意义上 我的意思是 你已经谈过了 你现在也在谈论 你最近说过意识形态发生了变化 你之前说意识形态只是一个谎言
but now it's a more cynical thing in a very precise sense that you know what you're doing.
但现在它是一种更加玩世不恭的东西 非常准确地说 你知道你在做什么
I would call it lie in the guise of truth.
我会称它为掩饰成真相的谎言
But what does this do then to the old enlightenment mind, this idea that everyone is a kind of, which you've written about as well, that we're sort of rational actors and we can make these decisions
但这对旧的启蒙心智意味着什么 这种观念 每个人都是一种理性行动者 我们可以做出这些决定
if you're in this kind of total paradise?
如果你处于这种完全的天堂中怎么办
I remain fully, although many people would not believe me, a guy of enlightenment.
我仍然完全是 尽管很多人可能不相信我 一个启蒙时代的人
What I'm saying is not that since rational argumentation doesn't work,
我所说的不是因为理性论证不起作用
then whatever, just violence or do nothing and so on, no.
然后无论如何 只是暴力或什么都不做 不
I think that there are different even strategies of speaking, where you can undermine this stance.
我认为甚至有不同的说话策略可以破坏这种立场
And I even, in one of my earlier books, I forgot which one, there are too many of them,
我甚至在我的一本早期书中 我忘了是哪一本了 它们太多了
I elaborated this how every apparently cynical guy, usually you have a fetish, an exception.
我详细阐述了这一点 几乎每个表面上玩世不恭的家伙 通常都有一个“执着” 一个例外 （译注：fetish 往往译为“恋物癖” 指的是个人对某些非生殖性的物体或特定情境有着强烈的性兴奋感 我个人在此处和后文将其译为“执着” 感觉更为合适）
And there is where you have to attach it.
那就是你需要抓住的地方
Maybe some of you know this example that I used years ago.
也许你们中的一些人知道我多年前使用的这个例子
It's real life, very stupid.
这是真实生活中的 非常愚蠢
A friend of mine, this was 30 years ago, 20,
我的一个朋友 这是30年前 20年前
had a wife who was, sorry for this sexist sounding, but beautiful young, they loved each other all you want.
有一个妻子 对不起这听起来有些性别歧视 但她年轻美丽 他们彼此相爱 一切都很好
And then all of a sudden in her mid-20s, she got breast cancer and it was too late.
然后突然在她25岁左右时 她得了乳腺癌 而且为时已晚
She died in two months, horrible.
她在两个月内就去世了 太可怕了
And we were so surprised that the guy, the husband, just went on functioning like normally,
我们非常惊讶那个丈夫 就像平常一样继续运作
talked even about the last moments of his wife, and then something happened.
甚至谈论他妻子的最后时刻 然后发生了一些事情
His wife had a preferred pet object, a small hamster.
他的妻子有一个喜欢的宠物 一只小仓鼠
Half a year later, this hamster died.
半年后 这只仓鼠死了
The guy immediately tried to kill him.
那个男人立刻试图自杀
You know, hamster was his fetish.
你知道 仓鼠是他的“执着”
It embodied like the wife somehow as a fetish, it was a disavowal of his wife's death.
它某种方式象征着他的妻子 作为一个“执着” 它是对他妻子死亡的一种否认
So it was at that point that he totally broke down, he had to be for one month on a, how do you call it, suicide watch, you know.
所以正是在那个时刻 他完全崩溃了 他不得不在自杀观察下呆了一个月 你知道
Always somebody with him.
总是有人陪着他
And tomorrow, to make a little bit of propaganda, at my speech about surplus enjoyment, enjoyment or maybe even at the theological debate in the afternoon, I will go into another forum of this.
而明天 为了做一点宣传 在我关于剩余享乐的演讲中 享乐或许甚至在下午的神学辩论中 我将进入这个话题的另一个形式
I was so fascinated with the figure of Heinrich Himmler, SS boss, who was formally, formally as to form, an extremely ethical guy.
我对海因里希·希姆勒这个人物非常着迷 他是党卫军领导
Never heard, but he organized Holocaust.
几不可闻 但他组织了大屠杀
But for him, this was the highest ethical act.
但对他来说 这是最高的伦理行为
And you know, he used a terrifying reversal here, this cynicism at its purest.
你知道 他在这里使用了一个可怕的反转 这是纯粹的讽刺
He admitted it, this is horrible.
他承认这是可怕的
How can we, decent Germans,
我们 体面的德国人
Do this, killing Jewish children,
怎么能这样做 杀害犹太儿童
we mean not even, and remain decent.
我们甚至无法保持体面
You know what was his answer?
你知道他的答案是什么吗
Oriental spiritualism.
东方精神主义
He always was carrying in his pocket a special leather copy of Bhagavad Gita,
他总是随身携带一本特制皮革版的《薄伽梵歌》
where you have this idea, you know, the king is convinced to go into battle, saying life is an appearance, the main thing is to do your duty.
在那里你有这个观点 你知道 国王被说服参加战斗 说生命是一种表象 最重要的是履行你的职责
And the really horrible thing, You find the same rhetorical trick in Stalinism with Trump today.
而真正可怕的事情是 你在斯大林主义中 今天的特朗普中找到相同的修辞技巧
It's, we all have, as I used it in my example, you know, this, I call it basic common sense decency.
它是 我们都有 正如我在我的例子中使用的 你知道 这个 我称之为基本的常识性体面
Like, certain thing you may, I don't, dream about them, I'm not saying I don't have dirty dreams, just not that kind.
像 有些事情你可能 梦想它们 我不是说我没有肮脏的梦 只是不是那种类型
But that's not part of the life conversation.
但这不是生活谈话的一部分
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
是的 是的 是的
Or maybe it is, I don't know.
或许它是 我不知道
No, no, no, what I don't, don't be afraid.
不 不 不 我不 不要害怕
No, no, no, what I just wanted to say is that The problem of Hitler is how do you remain sane and so on.
不 不 不 我只是想说 希特勒的问题是如何保持理智
And he operates a very dirty trick.
他使用了一个非常肮脏的技巧
He says that every idiot can be decent and fight for his country.
他说 任何傻瓜都可以为他的国家体面地战斗
But true patriotism is that you are ready to do horrible things for your country.
但真正的爱国主义是 你准备为你的国家做可怕的事情
And I discovered in how they were making propaganda for collectivization in 1930s, early 30s,
我发现在他们如何在20世纪30年代初期为集体化制作宣传时
when they collectivized and millions died of hunger in Russia, and I found the same figure.
当他们进行集体化 俄罗斯有数百万人饿死时 我发现了相同的论点
They said, you will see horrible things, peasant farmers, families starving and so on, but your decency is the greatest temptation to evil.
他们说 你会看到可怕的事情 农民 家庭挨饿等等 但你的正派是对邪恶的最大诱惑
If you're a true Bolshevik, you go on killing.
如果你是真正的布尔什维克 你应该继续杀戮
And this horrible ethics is returning to David Trump.
这种可怕的伦理回到了大卫·特朗普
But no.
但不是
Yes, yes.
是的 是的
I want to ask you a bit in terms of appearances as well that we take for realities.
我想问你一点 就是我们把表象看作现实
And I was thinking about Hegel in A Wired Brain where you're talking all about Hegel
我在想《连线大脑中的黑格尔》中你讨论的所有关于黑格尔和主体性
and subjectivity and how Hegelian notions of subjectivity might relate to this kind of strange world we're now in where for the first time, you know,
以及黑格尔的主体性观念如何与我们现在这个奇怪的世界有关 现在我们第一次
the Russians wanted to do this in the Soviet Union, but now we actually begin to have this technology where where we can create these strange singularities,
苏联的俄罗斯人想要这样做 但现在我们实际上开始拥有这种技术 我们可以创造这些奇怪的奇点
which you write about where brain-computer interfaces can link brains into this potentially, yes, potentially.
你写过的 大脑-计算机接口可以将大脑连接成这种潜在的 是的 潜在的
Of course, it's still sci-fi, but the beginnings of these kinds of technologies.
当然 它仍然是科幻 但这类技术的开端
And I want to ask you about that.
我想问你这个
How then does that change to you, the notion first of subjectivity, which you write about,
那么 这对你来说 首先是主体性的概念（你写过的）以及自由意志、自主性的观念（关于谁控制大脑-计算机接口）有何改变
and also these ideas of free will, autonomy, in terms of who's controlling the brain-computer interface?
我不想浪费太多时间
I don't want to lose too much time.
所以关于自由 我试图在我的自由书的第一章中提供
So as to freedom, I try to provide in the first chapter of my freedom book, which will be out by Bloomsbury in the fall, I try to, the point is how to,
这本书将于秋季由Bloomsbury出版 我试图 关键是如何
in facing the neurobiological, however you call it, determinism, how to, under quotation marks, save freedom.
面对神经生物学的 无论你如何称呼它 决定论 如何 在引号中 “拯救”自由
Because I agree with some determinists like the German lady Sabine Hossenfelder.
因为我同意一些决定论者 比如德国女士Sabine Hossenfelder
She's very intelligent.
她非常聪明
She said that, she even doesn't argue.
她说 她甚至不争论
She said that the moment you accept naturalism, there simply is no space for freedom.
她说 从你接受自然主义的那一刻起 就根本没有自由的空间了
Freedom is a subjective concept.
自由是一个主观概念
So how to save freedom?
那么如何拯救自由呢
My answer is not that it's freedom already there in nature, but that the first thing to do is to open up nature, not in the sense of higher spirituality,
我的回答不是自由已经存在于自然中 而是首先要做的是打开自然 不是以更高的精神性的意义
but in the sense that nature is in itself ontologically incomplete open.
而是以自然本身在本体上不完整、开放的意义
Not only human, sorry, not only human culture, but nature.
不仅仅是人类文化 而是自然
What do I mean by ontological openness?
我所说的本体开放性是什么意思
For example, here I always opposed historicism, which says, for example, classical example, I use it often in books, to really understand Shakespeare,
例如 我总是反对历史主义 历史主义认为 例如 经典的例子 我经常在书中使用 要真正理解莎士比亚
you have to know the details of Elizabethan England and so on.
你必须知道伊丽莎白时代英格兰的细节等等
My idea is not to really understand Shakespeare.
我的想法不是真正理解莎士比亚
Shakespeare didn't understand himself.
莎士比亚自己也不理解自己
His work was full of inconsistencies, incomplete.
他的作品充满了矛盾 不完整
And if you come later, it's not an obstacle.
但即使你是一个后代的阅读者 这也不是一个障碍
You can even understand Shakespeare better than he understood himself.
你甚至可以比他自己更好地理解莎士比亚
And so in some sense, we are not just reading Shakespeare differently.
因此 从某种意义上说 我们不仅仅是以不同的方式阅读莎士比亚
We are literally completing his work.
我们实际上是在完成他的作品
That's how I hate the official dogma of multiculturalism.
这就是我讨厌官方多元文化主义教条的原因
But I respect it when you really get it.
但当你真正理解它时 我尊重它
For example, maybe some of you heard this.
例如 也许你们中的一些人听说过这个
I find it so wonderful that the best Shakespeare cinema version that I know.
我觉得最棒的莎士比亚电影版本是我所知道的
It's done by Akira Kurosawa, 61 or two.
是由黑泽明在61或62年拍摄的
The version of Hamlet set in contemporary Japan.
这个版本的哈姆雷特设定在当代日本
Hamlet is a Japanese student returning from the United States.
哈姆雷特是一位从美国返回的日本学生
His father was a big corporate boss.
他的父亲是一位大公司的老板
But it, and it has a wonderful title, this movie.
但这部电影有一个很棒的标题
Only bad people sleep well.
只有坏人才能睡个好觉 （译注：《懒夫睡汉》）
It's a wonderful title.
这是一个很棒的标题
They don't care.
他们不在乎
But what I want to say is that I am ready,
但我想说的是 我已经准备好了
Maybe I'm speculating too much.
可能我推测得太多了
I'm now trying to study in detail as much as I can understand.
我现在正尽我所能详细研究量子物理学
Quantum physics, because I think what you find at the bottom of quantum physics is this idea of ontologically incomplete universe, in the sense that, in what sense?
因为我认为在量子物理学的底层 你会发现一个本体论上不完整的宇宙的概念 是什么意思呢
Sorry, give me two minutes.
对不起 给我两分钟
It's an old story, but I like to repeat it of mine.
这是一个老故事 但我喜欢重复
because it links to the previous debate at video games.
因为它和之前关于视频游戏的辩论有关
Look, the first thing about video games is that their universe is incomplete.
看 关于视频游戏的第一件事是 它们的宇宙是不完整的
You're in a game, stupid game, where you are shooting, fighting on the main street of a small town, let us say, and in the back you see forest with trees.
你在一个愚蠢的游戏中 你在一个小镇的主街上射击、战斗 背后你看到了树林
But it's not part of the game that you can approach those trees and see them in detail.
但游戏的一部分不是你可以靠近那些树并详细看到它们
It's part of the game, did you ever go there?
这是游戏的一部分 你有没有去过那里
So the programmer say, why lose time on that programming?
所以程序员说 为什么要浪费时间编程呢
Let's leave it open.
让我们留下它开放
And the way, I got this from a popular introduction to philosophy, sorry, forgot the name, but very intelligently, I think written.
我从一本流行的哲学入门书中得到这个 对不起 忘记了名字 但我认为写得很聪明
The guy says, is not quantum physics, does it not have the same lesson?
那家伙说 量子物理学难道不是同样的教训吗
When God was programming the universe, he said, people are too stupid to reach beyond the atom.
当上帝在编程宇宙时 他说 人们太愚蠢了 无法超越原子
so why should I bother their programming?
所以我为什么要费心编程呢
He lived it undetermined.
他让它不确定
And we were a little bit too bright for God, and we, as you say in English, caught God with his pants down, as it were.
我们对上帝来说有点太聪明了 正如你们英语所说 我们在上帝脱裤子的时候撞见他
You know?
你知道吗
And in fact, do you then believe then, or are you positing in terms of that argument?
实际上 你是否因此相信 或者你在这个论点中提出了什么
So are you saying, or maybe it's not possible, within quantum physics this question, is reality discrete or continuous?
所以你是说 或许这在量子物理学中是不可能的 这个问题 现实是离散的还是连续的
So is reality like Minecraft, where you kind of zoom in further and further and further, and then you get, as you say, down further, further to these tiny little, you know, to the leptons, and further and further down.
所以现实是像《我的世界》那样 你可以一直放大进入 然后你会得到 正如你所说 进一步深入 到达这些微小的 你知道 到达轻子 然后再进一步深入
Is that a view that you're a little sympathetic to?
这是一个你会赞同的观点吗
I spontaneously, but I don't have any empirical ground for this.
我是自发的 但我没有任何实证基础
I am for discrete nature in mod sense, and I think this is almost maybe the lesson of quantum physics, but I'm very much speculating now.
我倾向于离散的自然观 在某种意义上 我认为这几乎也许是量子物理的教训 但我现在进行更多的推测
I think that it's not this endless divisibility you can further split that.
我认为它不是这种无尽的可分割性 你可以进一步分割它
At certain point, I can split this in half, this and that, this and that.
在某种点上 我可以把这个一分为二 这个和那个 这个和那个
But I believe when you approach the zero point, the division is between something and nothing.
但我相信当你接近零点时 分割是在某物和无之间
You see, you get something, its counterpoint is void, is nothing.
你看 你得到了某物 它的对立面是虚无 是无
And so I'm not saying this is bad metaphysical reading of that in this freedom is grounded.
所以我并不是说这是对这种自由的根基的形而上学的糟糕解读
No, first, freedom is not contingency.
不 首先 自由不是偶然性
It's not my free act if I, but even this is not, of course, it's deterministic, but let's say for me it's a contingency.
这不是我的自由行为 但即使这不是 当然 这是决定性的 但对我来说这是偶然性的
It's to make a decision, I throw a coin up and set hat tail or whatever.
如果做决定时我抛硬币说正面或反面
No, that's contingency from my view, really it's not.
不 那是我的观点中的偶然性 实际上不是
But freedom is a necessity of its own.
但自由是其自身的必然性
Freedom is a positive decision that you do.
自由是你所做的积极的、建设的决定
Is this only, as they say, user's illusion?
这仅仅是 如他们所说 用户的幻觉吗 （译注：在技术和哲学领域 这个概念被用来描述用户对某些技术系统的误解或误解感知 这种错觉通常源于设计师有意或无意地创造的界面或体验 使用户感觉到的操作或体验方式并不完全反映了底层的机制或实际发生的事情 ）
I think not.
我认为不是
I think we have to, it's more important than ever, we have to accept this ontological openness of nature already, of history.
我认为我们必须 这比以往任何时候都更重要 我们必须接受自然的本体论开放性 历史的开放性
For example, we are now in an open situation, and retroactively it will become necessary.
例如 我们现在处于一个开放的局面中 而事后它将变得必然
If there will be a world war,
如果会爆发世界大战
if there will be people who will survive it,
如果有人能够幸存下来
They will tell the story of how it was all pointed towards this war.
他们会讲述这一切是如何指向这场战争的故事
We were doomed.
我们注定了
If there will not be a war, they will say, oh, it was like Cold War, false alarms, and so on.
如果不会有战争 他们会说 哦 那就像冷战 假警报等等
What I'm claiming is that these are not simply illusions.
我要说的是 这些不仅仅是幻觉
The situation is genuinely open.
情况确实是开放的
And another lesson, which I know it's not legitimate, I applied too quickly from quantum physics to humanities, nonetheless, is that to understand something, a historical event,
另一个教训 我知道这不合适 我过于迅速地从量子物理应用到人文科学 尽管如此 是要理解某个历史事件
you should read it in a superposition with other possible events.
你应该将其与其他可能的事件一起读取
When something happens, you should always ask yourself what other options failed so that this could have happened.
当某事发生时 你应该总是问自己哪些其他选项失败了 以至于这能发生
So in this way, back to our point immediately, My point in Wirebrained is a more optimistic one.
所以这样 立刻回到我们的点 我的观点是更乐观的
It's not just dark end of humanity.
这不仅仅是说 人类的黑暗末日
I try to, and it's so interesting that nobody likes those final concluding chapter, where I try to do exactly this, to ask this absolutely naive question.
我尝试这样做 这很有趣 没有人喜欢最后的结论章节 我尝试这样做 问这个绝对天真的问题
Maybe it's even the wrong question.
也许这甚至是错误的问题
Let's say that this, self-objectivization, in the sense of a machine which can read our mind.
比如说 这种自我客观化 以一台可以读取我们思想的机器的意义来说
Let's say that it more or less succeeds.
假设它或多或少成功了
We have it.
我们拥有了它
Does this mean that we no longer exist as subjects?
这是否意味着我们不再作为主体存在
My answer is an optimist one there.
我的答案是乐观的
First, by subject we should not understand this inner wealth of personality, but the pure Cartesian subjectivity.
首先 我们所理解的主体性并不是个性的内在财富 而是纯粹的笛卡尔式的主体性
That empty space will remain supported in what?
那个空的空间将以什么而保持支撑
In the unconscious.
在潜意识中
Because I have here quite an unconscious for me.
因为我这里有相当多的潜意识
It's not deep ingrained in our brain.
它并不深植于我们的大脑中 （译注：这里指的是无意识的内容或存在并不是生物学上固有的 而是后天形成的心理结构或过程）
Think about unconscious as just some kind of a purely symbolic virtual entity, something that exists, not materially, really.
将潜意识视为某种纯粹象征性的虚拟实体 某种实际上并非物质存在的东西 （译注：无意识应被视为一种象征性的、虚拟的存在 它不是物理意义上的实体 而是由人的思想和语言构建的）
But just as a, like, we have three, four versions that we think about.
但就像我们考虑的三、四个版本一样 （译注：我们对无意识有几种不同的理解或解释）
But to account for these versions,
但要解释这些版本
You have in your symbolic space to presuppose another option.
你必须在你的象征性空间中预设另一个选项 （译注：在我们构建对无意识的理解时 需要在我们的思考框架或“象征空间”中加入新的假设或可能性）
And unconscious is, in this sense, purely virtual.
而潜意识 在这种意义上 纯粹是虚拟的 （译注：无意识作为一种象征性构建的虚拟本质 强调它的非物质、非直观性质）
You know, you must have heard, maybe even here, two years ago when I repeated this story about wonderful anecdote.
你知道的 你一定听说过 可能是两年前我在这里重复讲过的那个关于奇妙轶事的故事
It's overused from the movie Ninotzka.
它被电影《尼诺奇卡》过度使用了
You know, a guy goes to a cafeteria and bring me coffee.
你知道的 一个人去咖啡馆 叫服务员给他来杯咖啡
He said, can I get coffee but without cream?
他说 我能不能要一杯不加奶油的咖啡
And the waiter answers correctly.
服务员正确地回答了
Sorry, sir.
对不起 先生
We don't have cream, only milk.
我们没有奶油 只有牛奶
So can I give you coffee without milk?
那我能给你来一杯不加牛奶的咖啡吗
That's in the, let's say consciousness is what I see.
那在我看来 就是所谓的意识
In any case, I get just plain coffee.
无论如何 我得到的只是普通咖啡
But it's a big difference if it's coffee without milk or coffee without cream.
但如果是不加牛奶的咖啡还是不加奶油的咖啡 区别很大
You will say I'm bullshitting.
你会说我在胡说八道
No, think about feminism.
不 想想女权主义
Isn't the big change in the history of feminism where women got it dead.
女权主义历史上的一大变革就是女性明白了这一点
Women who suffer, what they are deprived of is not milk but cream, if I can put it like this.
受苦的女性 她们被剥夺的不是牛奶而是奶油 如果我可以这么说
That is to say that it's not that they have a prescribed place in the symbolic space and that maybe if the husband is too brutal, no death.
也就是说 并不是他们在象征空间有规定的位置 也许如果丈夫没有那么残暴 就不会死
That what they are deprived of, their freedom and so on, needs a more radical shift.
她们被剥夺的 她们的自由等等 需要一个更激进的转变
So the first step in feminism, and I got this from Judith Butler, with whom I have many polymics, but I agree with her here, is to first, to clearly formulate what you are deprived of.
所以女权主义的第一步 我从朱迪思·巴特勒那里得到这个观点 尽管我和她有很多争论 但在这里我同意她 首先要清晰地阐述你被剥夺了什么
It's not enough to say, oh, my husband doesn't give me enough money and so on, blah, blah, blah.
仅仅说 哦 我的丈夫不给我足够的钱什么的 等等 这些都不够
No, you have to say the whole system which puts my husband, if we are living in traditional patriarchal society, is wrong.
不 你必须说这个将我的丈夫放于这个位置的体系——如果我们生活在传统父权社会中——是错误的
So to conclude, not with that long joke, I will tell you another thing, did you see Francois?
所以总结一下 不是那个长笑话 我要告诉你另一件事 你见到弗朗索瓦了吗
Yeah.
是的
No time.
没有时间了
My God.
我的天啊
Look, and they see, they think we live in free society.
看 他们认为我们生活在自由社会
No, no.
不 不是
We live in oppressive society.
我们生活在一个压迫性社会